YWCA of the U.S.A. Records. Record Group 7. Student Work
Sophia Smith Collection
Various studies, plans, and reports produced between the mid-1970s and early-1990s reiterated the combination of external and internal factors that contributed to the drastic decline in Student YWCAs. In addition to general postwar trends, by the later 1970s, the YWCA was suffering from students' general lack of interest in fostering or maintaining organizations and more and more students were troubled by the 'C' in YWCA. Because of its diminished profile, the YWCA was not perceived as an activist or feminist organization and it became ever more difficult to find skilled advisers. Primary YWCA issues related to the empowerment of women and racial justice were integrated into campus life through women's and multicultural centers and the institutionalization of women and minority/ethnic studies within the academy. And continued budget cuts at the national level meant the popular summer program opportunities were abandoned.
Lacking the staff and funding to found new Student Associations, in 1987 the Committee on Membership in the National Association (MINA) approved a plan to help establish a YWCA presence on campuses where none existed through the Registered Student Group plan. Registered Student Groups would function in cooperation with established (and often staffed) campus women's centers or organizations and offer a means for "relating in a structured manner" to the national student YWCA. RSG members could be elected to the National Student Council and attend regional and national meetings and events. A handful of such groups existed at least until 1998.
While all of the studies acknowledged the "historically invaluable contribution" and disproportionate impact of the Student YWCA on the movement as a whole, the National Association, which continued to experience severe budget restrictions, did not have the resources to address the particular problems of Student YWCAs, but also did not take action to eliminate the program. As of the 2001 Convention, 12 Student YWCAs were affiliated with the YWCA of the USA.
Administrative History
1906-23 Student Committee of the Home Departmentt, later Method Dept./Research and Method
1923-24 Student Department of the Field Division
1940-53 Student Division
1953-71 College and University Division
1972-75 Youth Constituencies Unit (includes Teens, Students, Young Adult)
1975-92 Services to Student Associations (SSA), sometimes listed under Field Services
1992- Member Association Services (MAS) Office, Student
Forms part of the YWCA of the U.S.A. Records.
NOTE: For the most part, the Microfilmed Records and the Original Format Records do not duplicate each other and both should be consulted. This description covers materials in both formats. See the Contents List for a folder-level inventory of the Original Format Records. See the Microfilmed Records Reel Lists for a detailed inventory of the microfilm.
The Student Materials consist of minutes; newsletters and other publications; reports; subject and reference files; mailings; a small amount of correspondence; work plans; conference and training materials; and files on individual Student Associations.
The Student YWCA was a unique 'constituent group' within the National Association, operating as its own organizational unit through most of the history of the organization. The various functions that were divided among multiple departments in service of the Community Associations were all carried out by the Student staff on behalf of Student Associations. The records, therefore, are somewhat like an association within the National Association.
As is the case generally with the National Association records, the bulk of the Student materials date from 1906 to 1970, the interval covered by the microfilmed Central File and Minutes and Reports. Little has survived for the period between 1970 and 1988. There are some 1988 to 2001 records, but because the Student movement was greatly reduced in size by that time, it is a modest amount.
The materials are rich with detail about the Students' part in most of the YWCA's traditional areas of concern. Minutes and reports, publications, and Council and Region records contain key materials for understanding the interracial work of the YWCA since staff with responsibility for "colored" and American Indian work were first hired by the Student Committee to work in "colored" and Indian schools. The students' enthusiastic efforts in "Interracial Education" after World War I and later involvement in Civil Rights Movement are also well documented.
Files on Programs and Projects, as well as "Cooperation" chronicle the students' participation in the YWCA's continued efforts to be a socio-economically diverse organization, through clubs and summer programs designed to help them learn about the lives, issues, and concerns of young employed women who did not go to college.
Health education, and particularly sex education was a central concern of the Student YWCA from the beginning of the movement. Minutes and reports, in particular, document this aspect of the program from the organized "positive health" campaign after World War I through the "Sex-Ins"-- information sessions on women's sexuality--on college campuses in the late 1960s.
As with the records of other "constituent groups" the National Association's leadership training efforts are also well documented. Materials on effective group work and administrative practice can be found in the Assembly, Conference, Council, and Training files, and in Publications.
Student Committee and Staff minutes and reports are some of the best sources of information about the YWCA's program of religious education. Concern over college students' tendency to abandon religion led the National Association to pay particular attention to the content of and methods for engaging college students in deeper thinking about religion. Some of the staff members most closely associated with the YW's religious program worked for the Student Department and Student secretaries taught religion courses in the Training School.
Since the students were responsible for proposing many of the more radical Convention resolutions and additions to the Public Affairs Program, the materials record not only the formation of these resolutions, but also vigorous advocacy on their behalf. Advocacy activities are documented in the Conference and Council materials as well as in publications, especially newsletters put out by the National Student Council. In addition, the materials provide evidence of the students' impatience with the pace of change in the National Association, particularly from the 1960s on, as the "generation gap" became more acute.
The Organization files are a good source of information about national and international student Christian organizations and their activities from the intense activity of the early years through their general decline as the twentieth century wore on. Documentation about YMCA-YWCA joint activities is particularly strong.
Prior to the establishment of the Services to Student Associations office in 1975, the Student Division does not seem to have maintained files on individual Associations. Reports written by regional staff (in the Region section) are the best source of earlier information on individual Student Associations.
Microfilmed Records, 1906-70 only
[see Microfilmed Records Reel List]
Materials under 'Student' include extensive Conference, Council and Region records as well as files on the National Intercollegiate Christian Council/National Student Council of the YM and YW, Training, Projects, World Student Christian Federation, Young Men's Christian Association, and miscellaneous subjects. The materials are arranged alphabetically.
Microfilmed records also include information about requirements for membership of Student Associations in the National; Student Assembly materials in Convention files; records of Student-Rural Projects; and information about the students' public advocacy under 'Public Affairs.'
Most of the Student materials were discarded after microfilming, so it is crucial to consult the microfilm. They can be found in:
Minutes and Reports
Student Committee
Basic Standards Committee [for Student Associations]
Standards Study Committee
Subject Files
Student
Convention, Student Assembly
Rural, Ford Studies, Student-Rural
Public Affairs [various Student programs and activities]
Original Format Records, 1906-2000, 34 linear feet
[see Original Format Records folder list]
Most of the Student records were discarded after microfilming, so it is crucial to consult the microfilm.
The bulk of the surviving paper records are dated from the 1920s through the 1960s. While these generally duplicate materials on the microfilm, they include some office "working files" that were transferred to the YWCA Archives after the Central File had been filmed and some of these materials, dating from the 1960s, are probably not on the film.
The paper records contain student publications that were not included in the microfilm, particularly joint YM-YW publications, such as the serial The Intercollegian.
1970-2000 (post-microfilm) materials include what appear to be the major reports on and studies of the Student work, as well as records of attempts to revitalize the Student movement through the revival of dormant Associations, establishment of new ones, or establishment of Registered Student Groups. There are also a few records about the Alumnae Skills Network, an effort to foster Student YWCA graduates' continued involvement in the YWCA through donations or volunteer work.
There are also files on individual Student Associations dating primarily from the mid-1970s to 2000. These include basic organizational documents such as constitutions, accreditation and other reports, records of staff visits, correspondence, and some information about program.
See also Related Materials.
The paper records are arranged in 11 series as follows:
I. GENERAL AND HISTORY
II. COMMITTEES
III. DEPARTMENT/DIVISION
IV. CONFERENCES
V. COUNCIL
VI. NATIONAL STUDENT ASSEMBLY
VII. ORGANIZATIONS
VIII. PROGRAMS AND PROJECTS
IX. PUBLICATIONS
X. REPORTS
XI. STUDENT ASSOCIATIONS AND REGISTERED STUDENT GROUPS
The records are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection without any additional restrictions.
Access to audiovisual materials may first require production of research copies.
Additional Formats
A copy of the microfilmed records of the YWCA of the U.S.A. Records is available to borrow from the William Allan Neilson Library at Smith College via Interlibrary Loan.
To request the microfilm from our library you will need to submit the following information to your library's Interlibrary Loan department:
Author: Young Women's Christian Association of the U.S.A. National Board
Title: Records, 1876-1970 [microform]
WorldCat Accession Number: OCLC 57415795
Notes: "Call # 689" and reel number(s) you want to borrow
Full descriptions and reel lists of the microfilm are available online.
The YWCA of the U.S.A. donated a portion of its records to the Sophia Smith Collection in 1964 and the remainder in 2002 and 2003.
Race awareness--United States; Race relations--United States; Student Volunteer Movement for Foreign Missions; World Student Christian Federation
Record Groups
The YWCA of the USA Records are arranged as follows:
YWCA of the U.S.A. Records (main record)
RECORD GROUP 1. GENERAL AND HISTORY
RECORD GROUP 2. PREDECESSOR ORGANIZATIONS AND NATIONAL BOARD
RECORD GROUP 3. NATIONAL ADMINISTRATIVE OFFICE
RECORD GROUP 4. NATIONAL CONVENTIONS AND CONFERENCES
RECORD GROUP 5. INTERNATIONAL WORK
RECORD GROUP 6. PROGRAM
RECORD GROUP 7. STUDENT WORK
RECORD GROUP 8. COMMUNITY ASSOCIATIONS
RECORD GROUP 9. PHOTOGRAPHS
RECORD GROUP 10. AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS
Artifacts
The Microfilmed Records
The Oversized Materials
This Record group forms part of the YWCA of the U.S.A. Records
In other Record Groups
RECORD GROUP 2. PREDECESSOR ORGANIZATIONS AND NATIONAL BOARD contains records of the primarily student American Committee. In addition, the Student YWCA is a frequent subject in National Board minutes and reports.
Activities of the Student YWCA and its staff are frequently reported in the YWCA's main serial, The AssociationMonthly/Womans Press/YWCA Magazine in SERIES VI. PUBLICATIONS of RECORD GROUP 6 PROGRAM.
The Student YWCA was under the direction of the Home Department/Research and Method Department prior to the establishment of the National Student Council in 1920. Records are in RECORD GROUP 6. PROGRAM.
Convention records in RECORD GROUP 4. NATIONAL CONFERENCES AND CONVENTIONS contain regular reports on the Student work, on Student Assemblies at Convention, and records of Resolutions initiated by the Student YWCA.
Materials related to Membership, and the Student YWCA's push to change the "basis" of individual membership in the YWCA are in SERIES III. MEMBERSHIP OF INDIVIDUALS in RECORD GROUP 1. GENERAL AND HISTORY.
RECORD GROUP 10. AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS includes audio and videotapes of a few Student Conferences and Assemblies from the mid 1980s.
Elsewhere in the Sophia Smith Collection and Smith College Archives
Southern Women, the Student YWCA, and Race (1920-1944) Collection
The Smith College Archives houses records of the Smith College Association for Christian Work, a college Christian association affiliated with the YWCA
Series Descriptions
- SERIES I. GENERAL AND HISTORY
  This series consists of general historical materials such as timelines and pamphlets about the Student program; records of inter-departmental cooperative projects (Student-Industrial, Student-Rural); some general information on student interracial work including the 'Self-Audit on Total Integration in Student YWCAs and SCAs' (1966); a few financial records; and papers and dissertations about the Student YWCA. The materials is arranged alphabetically by subject.
- SERIES II. COMMITTEES
  This series consists of minutes and a small amount of other material related to various Committees, Commissions, 'Issue Networks,' and 'Task Groups' made up of members of the National Student Council, the student staff, and the National Board. It is arranged alphabetically.
- SERIES III. DEPARTMENT/DIVISION
  Material in this series relates to the work of the national and regional student staff. Included are policies, a small amount of correspondence, some reference materials, staff meeting minutes and reports, job descriptions, and work plans. Materials are arranged alphabetically.
- SERIES IV. CONFERENCES
  This series contains a small amount of surviving material about some national and regional student conferences. Of note are typed proceedings for the 1926-27 Council of Christian Associations Conference and fairly substantial materials from Geneva (mid-west) Region conferences in the 1960s.
- SERIES V. COUNCIL
  Surviving paper records for National Council consist mainly of workbooks, minutes, correspondence, and notes from Council meetings, 1960-72. Regional Council materials dated prior to World War I tend to be minutes and reports, post-War materials include mailings, local arrangements, training materials, and correspondence. The Geneva (mid-west) and Pacific Northwest Regions are especially well-documented from the 1930s through the 1960s. There are significant materials from the Rocky Mountain Region from the 1950s and 1960s.
- SERIES VI. NATIONAL STUDENT ASSEMBLY
  Included are minutes and reports, and planning, study and training materials for the YWCA's National Student Assembly. Earlier materials, 1922-40, consist primarily of minutes and reports.
- SERIES VII. ORGANIZATIONS
  This series consists of two Subseries: General, consisting of records of the National Student Council's participation in various national and international student and Christian organizations; and YMCA and YWCA, consisting of records of the organizations whose membership was primarily (though not always exclusively) the Student YMCA and YWCA. These include the Council of Christian Associations (CCA, 1921-30); the National Intercollegiate Christian Council (NICC, 1935-50), and the National Student Council of the YMCA and YWCA (NSCY, 1951-70).
  Materials include publications, committee/commission records, training materials, joint YM-YW Student staff meetings and conference materials.
- SERIES VIII. PROGRAMS AND PROJECTS
  This series contains correspondence, memoranda, mailings, proposals, and reports from a variety of Student Summer Projects and other training programs. The materials are arranged alphabetically. Joint YMCA-YWCA Programs and Projects are filed in SERIES VII.
- SERIES IX. PUBLICATIONS
  This series consists of YWCA publications by, for, or about students. Included are general pamphlets, administrative handbooks, religious education materials, newsletters, and program materials. The materials are arranged alphabetically by title. Publications put out jointly by the YM and the YW are filed under NICC/NSCY in SERIES VII.
- SERIES X. REPORTS
  This series contains general reports on the Student Program; annual reports of the Student Committee Chair and Department Executive; and periodic/quarterly reports by Student Secretaries/Staff. The bulk of the material is Secretary reports dated between 1908 and 1926. As elsewhere in the National Association records, the Secretary reports are a goldmine of information.
- SERIES XI. STUDENT ASSOCIATIONS AND REGISTERED STUDENT GROUPS
  General materials filed at the beginning of the series include lists of Student Associations and Registered Student Groups, general information about accreditation standards, and copies of report forms. These are followed by files on individual Student Associations which contain legal documents such as constitutions, accreditation and other reports, correspondence, reports of staff visits, and program materials. The bulk of the materials are dated 1975 and later. They are arranged alphabetically by state, then by institution.
- SERIES I. GENERAL AND HISTORY
  This is the Contents List for the Original Format Records only. The reel lists for the Microfilmed Records are in a separate file. See Scope and Content note for more description.
  - Miscellaneous, 1913-2000, n.d. (Box 736, Folder 1-2)
  - Brochures and pamphlets, general (Box 736, Folder 3)
  - By-laws, 1934-98 (Box 736, Folder 4)
  - Charts, circa 1960-65 (Box 736, Folder 5)
  - Cooperation (Box 736)
  - Student-City, 1926-29 (Box 736, Folder 6)
    - Student-Community, 1926-68 (Box 736, Folder 7-8)
    - Student-Industrial (Box 736)
  - General, 1926-59, n.d. (Box 736, Folder 9)
  - Conferences, 1921-31 (Box 736, Folder 10)
  - Summer Study/Student-in-Industry Programs, 1920-50 (Box 736, Folder 11)
  - Student-Girl Reserve/Teen, 1922, n.d. (Box 736, Folder 12)
  - Student-Rural, 1915 (Box 736, Folder 13)
  - Financial
    - General, 1912-66, 1999 (Box 737, Folder 1)
    - Alumnae Skills Network/Student Leadership Development Fund, 1982-95 (Box 737, Folder 2)
    - College and University YWCA Board Finance Packet, 1963 (Box 737, Folder 3)
    - Rocky Mountain Region, 1950-70, n.d. (Box 737, Folder 4-6)
  - Interracial
    - General, 1922-74, n.d. (Box 737, Folder 7-8)
    - Self-Audit on Total Integration in Student YWCAs and SCAs, 1966
      - Correspondence, 1966-67 (Box 737, Folder 9)
      - Compilation notes (Box 737, Folder 10)
      - Miscellaneous notes and reference materials (Box 737, Folder 11)
      - Report, Dec 1966 (Box 737, Folder 12)
      - Responses by state
        - A-C (Box 737, Folder 13)
        - D-W (Box 738, Folder 1-7)
  - Junior Colleges, 1923-38, 1966 (Box 738, Folder 8)
  - Papers and dissertations
    - "The Constitutional Relationship of the Student YWCAs to the YWCAs of the USA," 1940 (Box 738, Folder 9)
    - "The Future of YWCA Work with Students" position paper by Sara Kavich, 1978 (Box 738, Folder 10)
    - '"On the Edge of Tomorrow": Southern Women, the Student YWCA, and Race, 1920-44' by Frances Sanders Taylor, dissertation, Stanford University, 1984 (Box 738, Folder 11-12)
    - "The Student YWCA: Issues and Affirmations" by Margaret E. Norton, 1967 (Box 739, Folder 1)
  - Studies
    - Study of National Student Council: outline and raw materials, 1936-40, n.d. (Box 739, Folder 2-4)
    - National Student Survey (aka Student Study), 1994
      - General, 1992-94 (Box 739, Folder 5)
      - Student Study Committee, 1993-94 (Box 739, Folder 6)
      - Background papers, 1978, 1983 (Box 739, Folder 7)
      - Survey instruments (Box 739, Folder 8)
      - Notes on phone interviews and focus groups (Box 739, Folder 9)
      - Responses (Box 739, Folder 10)
      - Reports (Box 739, Folder 11)
  - Training
    - General, 1957-77, 1988, n.d. (Box 739, Folder 12)
    - Reference materials, 1955-64, n.d. (Box 739, Folder 13)
    - Cluster Meetings, 1984 (Box 739, Folder 14)
    - Faculty Advisors Workshops, 1962 (Box 739, Folder 15)
    - Leadership, 1956-60, n.d. (Box 739, Folder 16)
    - Management Workshop for Leadership in Student Associations, Nov 1981 (Box 739, Folder 17-18)
    - Program Planning, 1956-65, n.d. (Box 740, Folder 1)
    - Strategic Planning Student Leadership Summits, 1997 (Box 740, Folder 2)
    - "The System and Change" by Sally J. Timmel, 1970 (Box 740, Folder 3)
  - YMCA-YWCA Relationships, 1945-66, n.d. (Box 740, Folder 4-7)
- SERIES II. COMMITTEES
  - Student Committee: minutes
    - 1906-17 (Box 740, Folder 8-18)
    - 1918-21 (Box 741, Folder 1-4)
  - Student Department, 1922-23 (Box 741, Folder 5-6)
  - Executive Committee of the National Student Department, 1922-24 (Box 741, Folder 7-10)
  - [Full] Executive Committee of the National Student Council, 1924-47 (Box 741, Folder 11-14)
  - National Student Council [Resident] Executive Committee, 1924-28 (Box 741, Folder 15-16)
  - Resident/Headquarters Committee, 1928-46 (Box 742, Folder 1-8)
  - Administrative Committee of the National Student YWCA: minutes
    - 1947-58 (Box 742, Folder 9-15)
    - 1959-70 (Box 743, Folder 1-5)
  - National Student Steering Committee
    - Rosters, 1977-83 (Box 743, Folder 6)
    - Minutes, correspondence, and reports, 1979-85 (Box 743, Folder 7)
  - Executive Committee, College and University Division: minutes, 1959-68 (Box 743, Folder 8-11)
  - National Student Committee: minutes, 1968-71 (Box 743, Folder 12-13)
  - [National Board] Student Affairs Committee, 1978-87 (Box 743, Folder 14)
  - Ad-hoc Committee to Look at the National Student Movement, 1996 (Box 743, Folder 15)
  - Ad-Interim Committee, 1932-33 (Box 743, Folder 16)
  - Black Affairs Committee, 1968-76, n.d. (Box 743, Folder 17)
  - Budget Committee, 1929-31 (Box 744, Folder 1)
  - Business Committee of the National Student Council, 1923-24, 1926-28 (Box 744, Folder 2)
  - Business Committee of the Student Dept/Division: minutes, 1923-24 (Box 744, Folder 3)
  - Friendly Relations with Foreign/International Students, 1924-33 (Box 744, Folder 4-5)
  - Interracial/Interracial Education Committee, 1933-47 (Box 744, Folder 6)
  - Issue Networks
    - General, 1967-70 (Box 744, Folder 7)
    - Drug Abuse, 1971 (Box 744, Folder 8)
    - Economic Power, 1963-71 (Box 744, Folder 9)
    - Higher Education, 1969-70 (Box 744, Folder 10)
    - Women's Liberation, 1969 (Box 744, Folder 11)
  - New Directions in the Student YWCA Commission: report, 1968 (Box 744, Folder 12)
  - Personnel Committee: minutes, 1929-32 (Box 744, Folder 13)
  - Personnel and Finance Committee, 1957-58 (Box 744, Folder 14)
  - Personnel and Budget Committee, 1931-32 (Box 744, Folder 15)
  - Personnel Committee for Local Staff
    - General and reports, 1940-50 (Box 744, Folder 16)
    - Minutes, 1945-60 (Box 744, Folder 17-20)
  - Personnel Committee for National Staff, 1965-68 (Box 744, Folder 21)